Register of the Brutus Coste Papers, 1940-1985
Hoover Institution Archives
Brutus Coste Papers,
1940-1985
85051
Coste, Brutus, 1910-1985
85 manuscript boxes (35.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, dispatches, memoranda, reports, press releases, speeches and writings, conference proceedings, financial records, and printed matter, relating to Romanian diplomacy during World War II; discussion of Romania at the Paris Peace Conference of 1946; Romanian and other Eastern European emigre affairs; postwar anti-communist movements, especially the Assembly of Captive European Nations and the Truth about Romania Committee; and the status of human rights in Romania and elsewhere in Eastern Europe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
World War, 1939-1945 --Diplomatic history; Paris Peace Conference (1946); World War, 1939-1945 --Peace.; Anti-communist movements --United States; Romanians --United States; East Europeans --United States; ACEN (Organization); Truth about Romania Committee; Civil rights --Romania; Romania; Europe, Eastern; United States; World War, 1939-1945; Communism; World War, 1939-1945 --Romania; Romania --Foreign relations; Diplomats --Romania
Biographical Note
1910 Born in Ciacova, Romania
1933-1946 Member of the Romanian Diplomatic Service: Secretary and later Counselor of Romanian legations in Paris and London Also acted for a long time as charge d'affaires in the Romanian legations in Washington and Lisbon
March 1945-February 1946 Broke relations with the Communist-controlled Groza regime after it came to power in Romania Remained in control of the legation in Lisbon until the recognition by the Western powers of the communist government
1946-1947 Secretary General of the unofficial delegation of Major Romanian political parties at the Paris Peace Conference
1947 Moved to New York Political advisor to General Nicolae Radescu, the last democratic Prime Minister of Romania
1954-? Director of the International League for the Rights of Man, and representative of the organization to the U.N.
1954-1965 Secretary General of the Assembly of Captive European Nations
1965-1967 Staff Consultant to the Foreign Policy Research Institute of the University of Pennsylvania Special Assistant to the President of the Institute for American Strategy
1967- Associate Professor, then Professor Emeritus, of International Relations and World History at Fairleigh Dickinson University, N.J.
1973- Headed the Truth About Romania Committee since its inception
1985 Died in New York
Scope and Content Note
Brutus Coste's papers cover mainly the years he spent as an emigre in the U.S., during the years 1947-1985. Both his writings and correspondence deal mostly with émigré affairs.
Of main importance are the materials related to the Assembly of Captive European Nations, whose General Secretary Brutus Coste was for eleven years. The main message that Coste addressed through the A.C.E.N. was a criticism of the Johnson Administration policy of "building bridges" with Eastern European countries, which seemed to become more independent of Moscow. Coste claimed (see files 1,3,8 in box 11; files 4,8,14,16,22 in box 13) that American financial help only delayed liberalization and the fall of communism. In his interviews (see box 1) and correspondence (see boxes 6-9 and 39), Coste accuses the National Committee for a Free Europe (the sponsoring organization of both the A.C.E.N. and Radio Free Europe) for his removal from the presidency of the A.C.E.N. precisely because of his stance.
Also of great importance are the confidential reports sent to Romania by Coste from the Romanian legations in London, Washington, and Lisbon, 1940-1947, concerning the financial funds of the Romanian National Bank in the U.S; the financial transactions of the Swedish Legation in Washington, which took over the Romanian interests in the U.S.; and Romania between and after World War II. Among the recipients of his reports were Marshall Mihai Antonescu, Alexandru Cretzianu, Cornel Bianu, and Vasile Gregorcea.
Of special interest are the materials related to Father Gheorghe Calciu Dumitreasa, who was sentenced in 1979 to ten years of imprisonment for preaching religious freedom, after having already been imprisoned sixteen years during the Stalinist period. This collection contains records documenting the efforts of the Truth About Romania Committee, under the chairmanship of Brutus Coste; of the Committee for the Defense of Rev. Gheorghe Calciu, under the chairmanship of Mircea Eliade; and of the Committee of Intellectuals for a Free Europe, under the chairmanship of Eugene Ionesco, for the priest's release from prison.
Finally, of specific importance are Coste's and Radescu's papers related to forced labor in Romania (see files 1 in box 12 and box 20) and Coste's papers regarding the financial terms of the armistice in 1946 (box 11).
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1940-1985. (Boxes 1-2)
  Biographical sketches, clippings, obituaries, papers related to Coste's participation in various academic events and to his recall from the Romanian Legation in Lisbon, resumes, miscellaneous financial papers, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1947-1985. (Boxes 3-10)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1940-1981. (Boxes 11-15)
  Articles, papers, radio broadcast transcripts, reports, speeches, miscellaneous writings, and notes related to his course work, arranged chronologically by title
- SUBJECT FILE, 1940-1985. (Boxes 16-38)
  Correspondence, declarations, lectures, memoranda, notes, radio broadcast transcripts, reports, speeches, statements, studies, clippings and other printed matter, related mainly to Romanian politics and government, and to social and economic conditions in Romania, 1944-1989, to the Truth About Romania Committee, and Romanian émigré affairs in the U.S., arranged alphabetically by subject
- ASSEMBLY OF CAPTIVE EUROPEAN NATIONS, 1954-1965. (Boxes 39-52)
  Charter, correspondence, memoranda, press releases, publications, reports, resolutions, clippings and other printed matter, related to Coste's participation in, and to the activities of, the A.C.E.N., an organization of leaders in exile from nine Eastern European countries, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- PHOTOGRAPH, 1967. (Box 52)
  One print depicting Brutus Coste
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1940-1985
  - Biographical sketches, 1966-1976 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1945-1969 (Folder 2)
  - Obituaries, 1985 (Folder 3)
  - Resumes, 1975 (Folder 4)
  - Subject File
    - Academic career. Miscellaneous materials, 1966-1976. See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/ Miscellaneous notes (Folder 5)
    - Diplomatic career. Confidential reports, sent to Romania by Coste from the Romanian legations in London, Washington, and Lisbon, 1940-1947 (Folder 6-10)
    - Participation in the A.C.E.N., 1963-1965. Miscellaneous papers. See also ASSEMBLY OF CAPTIVE EUROPEAN NATIONS (Folder 11)
    - Recall to Romania from the Romanian Legation in Lisbon, Portugal, 1945. Miscellaneous papers (Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous financial papers, 1977-1984 (Box 2., Folder 1-6)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1947-1985.
  See also SUBJECT FILE/ Goma, Paul; Institute for American Strategy; National Committee for a Free Europe; Truth About Romania Committee; ASSEMBLY OF CAPTIVE EUROPEAN NATIONS
  - General, 1945-1985. Consists mainly of personal letters with friends
    - General
      - A-G (Box 3., Folder 1-11)
      - H-P (Box 4., Folder 1-11)
      - R-Z (Box 5., Folder 1-10)
    - Personal, 1945-1985 (Folder 11-14)
    - Personal (Box 6-8.)
    - Personal (Box 9., Folder 1-5)
  - Unidentified, 1947-1978 (Folder 6-10)
  - Bianu, Cornel, 1946 (Box 10., Folder 1)
  - Boila, Remus, 1963-1968 (Folder 2)
  - Bossy, Raul, 1957 (Folder 3)
  - Campeanu, Radu, 1982-1983 (Folder 4)
  - Cretzianu, Alexandru, 1947-1953 (Folder 5)
  - Crutzescu, R., 1949-1953. Includes correspondence with others regarding Crutzescu (Folder 6)
  - Danielopol, D. G., 1964 (Folder 7)
  - Davila, Carol, 1953-1957 (Folder 8)
  - Dragan, Iosif-Constantin, 1952-1970 (Folder 9)
  - Duca, George, 1976-1977 (Folder 10)
  - East-European Inquiry, 1953 (Folder 11)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1948-1978 (Folder 12)
  - Emmet, Christopher, 1960-1973 (Folder 13)
  - Farcasanu, Mihai, 1948 (Folder 14)
  - Floda, Liviu, 1977-1982 (Folder 15)
  - Fond Lisabona-Madrid, 1947-1948 (Folder 16)
  - Ford, Gerald, 1974-1976 (Folder 17)
  - Gafencu, Grigore, 1948-1956 (Folder 18)
  - Gaulle, Charles de, 1966 (Folder 19)
  - Georgescu-Roegen, 1978 (Folder 20)
  - Ghilezeanu (Ghilezan), Emil, 1964-1976. Includes papers related to his emigration to the U.S. (Folder 21)
  - Giscard d'Estaing, Valerie, 1975 (Folder 22)
  - Grigorcea, Ms., 1949 (Folder 23)
  - Humphrey, Hubert, 1968 (Folder 24)
  - Ileana, Princess of Romania, 1951-1975 (Folder 25)
  - Ionesco, Eugen, 1976 (Folder 26)
  - Ionnitiu, Mircea, 1968-1980 (Folder 27)
  - Kennedy, Robert, 1967 (Folder 28)
  - Kissinger, Henry, 1976 (Folder 29)
  - Lehrman, Hal, 1966 (Folder 30)
  - Lovestone, Jay, 1964-1979 (Folder 31)
  - Michael, King of Romania, n.d. (Folder 32)
  - National Strategy Information Center, 1968-1977 (Folder 33)
  - Nickels, 1948 (Folder 34)
  - Nixon, Richard, 1967-1968 (Folder 35)
  - Paul VI, Pope, 1973 (Folder 36)
  - Petre-Lazar, 1948 (Folder 37)
  - Radescu, Nicolae, 1948-1952 (Folder 38)
  - Ratiu, Ion, 1977-1984 (Folder 39)
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1984 (Folder 40)
  - Romanian Academic Society, 1962-1963 (Folder 41)
  - Rugina, Anghel, 1966-1967 (Folder 42)
  - San Diego State College, 1951 (Folder 43)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1962-1969 (Folder 44)
  - Visoianu, Constantin, 1948-1976 (Folder 45)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1940-1981.
  See also SUBJECT FILE/Foreign Policy Research Institute; Institute for American Strategy; National Committee for a Free Europe; Romanian National Committee; Romanians in foreign countries; Truth About Romania Committee; ASSEMBLY OF CAPTIVE EUROPEAN NATIONS
  - "Are the East-Central European Nations Evolving Toward Freedom and Independence?" n.d. Typescript. Includes Spanish translation (Box 11., Folder 1)
  - "CACEED Honoring Senator Todd," n.d. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Chronological Analysis," n.d. Typescript (Folder 3-4)
  - "Chronology: Summaries of the Charts," n.d. Notes and typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Eastern Europe and the Survival of the West," n.d. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Elections under Communism Save Time and Money," n.d. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Moscovites in the Romanian C.P. Leadership," n.d. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - Essay on East-Central Europe, n.d. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - Studies related to the Mid-European Studies Center, n.d. Notes and typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Resurgent Imperialism at the Crossroads of Dead Empires," n.d. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - "Romania and the Soviet Chinese Rift," n.d. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "The Satellites: Assets or Liabilities to the USSR," n.d. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - Untitled writings by B. Coste and Hall Lehrman, n.d. Typescripts (Folder 14)
  - "Population Living in the Territory Granted to Hungary," 1940. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - "The Problem of Bassarabia," 1941-1946. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - "Memorandum Concerning Romania Before World War Two and Her Russian Campaign Until 1943: Suggestions for the Future of Europe," 1943 March 15. Typescript (Folder 17)
  - "The Ability of Romania to Carry out Her Obligations Under the Armistice Terms Following Her Territorial Losses," 1946. Typescripts. See also SUBJECT FILE/ Romania - Politics and government, 1944-1949 (Folder 18-19)
  - "Romania and the Soviet Union," 1947. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - Considerations on forced labor in Romania, 1948. Typescripts (Box 12., Folder 1-3)
  - Studies related to Romanian refugees, 1948-1951. Typescripts (Folder 4)
  - "Historical Outline," 1949. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - "The Effect on Romanian Population of Meeting Quota," 1950. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Expediency as Foreign Policy," 1950. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Moral Aspects of a Projected East-West Deal," 1950. Notes and typescript (Folder 8)
  - "Propaganda in Eastern Europe," 1950. Typescript (Folder 9-11)
  - "Report on Recent Developments in Romania," 1950. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Romania After Five Years of Soviet Occupation," 1950. Typescripts (Folder 13)
  - "Survey of Industrial Production in Communist Romania," 1950. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Titoism," 1950. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - "The Twilight of Ana Pauker," 1950. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - WEVD broadcast transcripts, 1950-1966. Coste's interviews as a regular panelist in the Foreign Policy Round Table of the station. Notes and typescripts (Folder 17-18)
  - WEVD broadcast transcripts, 1950-1966 (Contd.) (Box 13., Folder 1)
  - "Our Allies Behind The Iron Curtain," lecture, Institute of World Affairs, San Diego, 1951. Notes, holograph, and typescript. Includes a memorandum (Folder 2-3)
  - "Memo to All Anti-Communists," 1953. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "Western Misconceptions on Eastern Europe," 1959. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Lecture, Institute of World Affairs, San Diego, 1961. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - Outline of lecture, New Orleans, 1964 February 20. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - Obituary for Elie Cristo-Loveanu, 1964 April 30. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - "Changes in Albania, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Poland and Romania," 1965 May. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "The Strategic Importance of East-Central Europe for the Cause of Freedom in Europe," 1965. Typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Bucharest and the Soviet Drive to Break-Up NATO," 1966, June. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - "Notes on the Warsaw Treaty: Statement Issued in Bucharest, on July 8, 1966," 1966 July 8. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Romania and the Red China," 1966 September. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - "Notes on 'Romania..Master of Its Own Fate' by Russell Jones," 1966. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - Papers on the myth of Ceausescu's independent policy towards Moscow, 1966-1976 (interviews, radio broadcasts, newspaper article). Typescripts (Folder 15)
  - Obituary for Stefan Irimescu, 1967 January 20. Typescript (Folder 16)
  - "A Revealing Speech of Romanian Party Head, Nicolae Ceausescu," 1967 February 28. Typescript (Folder 17)
  - "Alba Iulia, 1 Decembrie 1918, din perspectiva exilului," 1967. Typescript (Folder 18)
  - "Bonn Bucharest Tie," 1967. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - Study on Radio Free Europe, written for the Republican Campaign, 1967. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - "Romania Plays Deceptive Role," Manion Forum, 1968. Includes Romanian translation. Typescripts (Folder 21)
  - "A Survey on the Observance of Human Rights Throughout the World," 1968. Typescript (Folder 22)
  - "Some Lessons of the Czechoslovak Drama," 1968 September. Notes and typescript (Folder 23)
  - "U.S. Policy Toward Eastern Europe," 1968. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - "A New Eastern Europe?" 1969 June. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - "The Foreign Policy of the Communist Regime in Romania," 1969 August. Typescript (Folder 26)
  - Obituary for Constantin Abeles, 1969 October 15. Typescript (Folder 27)
  - Obituary for Ionel Perlea, 1970. Typescript (Folder 28)
  - "The Soviet Strategy in the World Politics Today," 1971 June. Typescript (Folder 29)
  - Address to the Carnegie Endowment, 1972 May 10. Typescript (Folder 30)
  - Considerations on Soviet politics, 1973. Typescript (Folder 31)
  - "Romania Wants Freedom," 1974 August. Typescript (Folder 32)
  - "Cuvint de 1 Decembrie 1974," 1974 December 1. Typescript (Folder 33)
  - "Working Conditions," 1975 April. Typescript (Folder 34)
  - Studies related to the Romanian National Committee, 1975. Typescripts (Folder 35)
  - "Indaratnicie Cumpanita si Inceata," 1978. Typescript (Folder 36)
  - "Soviet-Romanian Relations: Conflict or Cooperation?" 1979. Typescript (Folder 37)
  - "Zece Mai 1979," 1979. Typescript (Folder 38)
  - "Zece Mai 1981," 1981. Typescript (Folder 39)
  - Miscellany, 1948-1970 (Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1948-1977 (Box 14., Folder 1-11)
  - Miscellaneous notes related to Coste's course work at Fairleigh Dickinson University, 1968-1980 (Box 15., Folder 1-8)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1940-1985.
  Correspondence, declarations, lectures, memoranda, notes, radio broadcast transcripts, reports, speeches, statements, studies, clippings and other printed matter
  - Aber, Margit (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - Ciphers used in the correspondence of leading Romanian refugees among themselves (Folder 2)
  - Coste, Tantzi (Doris Green) (Folder 3-8)
  - Coste, Tantzi (Doris Green)(Contd.) (Box 17., Folder 1-6)
  - Council of Europe. Reports of the Consultative Assembly, 1962. Includes French version (Box 18., Folder 1-2)
  - Emmet, Christopher (Folder 3-7)
  - Europe, Eastern - Politics and government- 1945-1989. Clippings (Box 19., Folder 1-9)
  - Forced labor - Romania. Includes records of the Association of Romanian Journalists in the U.S., the International League for the Rights of Man, the Commission of Inquiry into Forced Labor; and statements of General Radescu, Emil Ghilezan, Adriana Cosmovici (Box 20., Folder 1-4)
  - Foreign Policy Research Institute. Materials related to the research project "The Implications of Evolutionary Trends in East Central Europe to Western and U.S. Security," 1967, to which Coste contributed (Box 21., Folder 1-5)
  - Foreign Policy Research Institute (Contd.) (Box 22., Folder 1-6)
  - Gafencu, Grigore (former Minister of Foreign Affairs). Statements, speeches, radio broadcast transcripts, lectures, and declarations (Folder 7)
  - Goma, Paul. Includes materials related to the efforts of Coste and the Truth About Romania Committee for Goma's release from prison in 1977. Contains also correspondence among Brutus Coste and Paul Goma, Mircea Eliade, Jay Lovestone, George Duca, Virgil Nemoianu, and others concerning Goma's visit to the U.S. in 1978 (Box 23., Folder 1-7)
  - Institute for American Strategy. Includes Coste's writings and correspondence as Special Assistant to the Director. Includes also materials related to the Freedom Studies Center, administered by the Institute (Folder 8-10)
  - Institute for American Strategy (Contd.) (Box 24., Folder 1-9)
  - International Peasant Union (Box 25., Folder 1-2)
  - Lehrman, Hal (Folder 3-5)
  - National Committee for a Free Europe. Documents concerning Coste's cooperation with the Committee; miscellaneous materials regarding Radio Free Europe (Box 26., Folder 1-5)
  - Radescu, Nicolae (former Romanian premier). Includes his statements, speeches, letters, radio broadcasts, and speeches related to his escape from Romania and emigration to the U.S.; includes also materials concerning the formation of the Romanian National Committee (Folder 6)
  - Radescu, Nicolae (Contd.) (Box 27., Folder 1-2)
  - Radio Free Europe. See National Committee for a Free Europe
  - Romania
    - Church. Includes materials related to Father Gheorghe Calciu Dumitreasa and Romanian Orthodox churches in New York, Cleveland, Michigan, Connecticut (Folder 3-7)
    - Foreign relations (Folder 8-10)
      - 1914-1944. Includes two original papers on Romanian foreign policy until 1944 by Grigore Niculescu-Buzesti and Alexandru Cretzianu
      - 1944-1989. Includes facsimile papers of Gheorghe Tatarescu and Iuliu Maniu (Folder 11)
    - History
      - 1914-1944. Includes a brochure entitled Transylvania: Object of Romanian and Hungarian Discord, by A. Popa; miscellaneous writings related to the Danubian Conference, 1940 (Box 28., Folder 1-2)
      - 1944-1989. Typescripts of Russian-Romanian Conventions, 1945-1946, including the Truce Convention; memoranda, commentaries, and meeting transcripts of the Paris Peace Conference, 1946, and interpretations of the Conference Treaty (Folder 3-7)
    - Law- 1944-1989. Transcripts of various decrees and international conventions, 1945-1946 (Folder 8)
    - Politics and government- 1944-1989. One brochure entitled Evidence of Violations of Peace Treaty Guaranties of Human Rights: Rumania, Bulgaria and Hungary; facsimiles of political declarations of Michael, King of Romania; Iuliu Maniu; Ion Mihalache; Grigore Niculescu-Buzesti; Romniceanu (1944-1946); miscellaneous facsimiles and clippings concerning the overthrow of the Romanian democratic government, 1945-1947. Includes also writings related to Romania's economic and financial effort during 1946-1952, under the armistice terms (Folder 9-10)
    - Politics and government- 1944-1989 (Contd.) (Box 29., Folder 1-10)
  - Romanian literature. Includes papers referring to the Romanian Library in Freiburg, Germany, and the book Omul Suspect, by Dan Petrasincu (Box 30., Folder 1-2)
  - Romanian National Committee (R.N.C.). Memorandum written by Coste and Gafencu concerning their interview at the U.S. State Department regarding the formation of the R.N.C.; important materials related to the formation of the Committee; miscellaneous brochures (Suppression of Human Rights in Romania, The Perversion of Education in Romania, Persecution of Religion in Romania); and issues of R.N.C. Information Bulletin, 1950-1951 (Folder 3-10)
  - Romanians in foreign countries, 1951-1961. Includes miscellaneous magazines of Romanian émigrés (B.I.R.E., Curierul Crestin, Preuves, Romania Muncitoare, Limite, Orizonturi, 1949-1953) containing articles by Brutus Coste, Mircea Eliade, Vintila Horia, George Caranfil, Raul Bossy, Anghel Rugina, Pierre Sergescu, Constantin Ghidel; miscellaneous materials regarding Romanian Cultural Association from UK. Includes also papers of, and letters written by or related to, W. Filderman, Alexandru Cretzianu, Emil Cioran, Mihail Farcasanu, Vasile Gregorcea, Anghel Rugina, George Duca (Box 31-32.)
  - Truth about Romania Committee (T.A.R.C.), 1940-1982. Includes Coste's correspondence and writings related to the T.A.R.C., one study on Bessarabia by Radu Crutzescu (1944), materials on the autonomy of Transylvania, T.A.R.C.'s "Memorandum on the Compliance of the Ceausescu Regime with the Final Act of the Helsinki Conference," confidential memoranda, reports, and correspondence of the T.A.R.C. (Box 33-34.)
  - Voice of America. Consists mainly of political analyses related to its project "Liberarea Romaniei," 1952-1953 (Box 35., Folder 1-4)
  - WEVD broadcasting station (Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous materials and clippings (Folder 6-7)
  - Miscellaneous materials and clippings (Contd.) (Box 36-38.)
- ASSEMBLY OF CAPTIVE EUROPEAN NATIONS (A.C.E.N.), 1954-1965
  - Charter and rules of procedure (Box 39., Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of Coste, in his capacity of Secretary General of the Assembly (Folder 2-4)
  - Memoranda (Folder 5)
  - Press releases (Box 40., Folder 1-2)
  - Publications
    - ACEN East-Central European Papers, 1958-1963 (Folder 3)
    - ACEN News (Box 41., Folder 1-4)
    - ACEN Official Report of the Debates, 1955-1957 (Box 42., Folder 1-4)
    - A Survey of Recent Developments in Nine Captive Nations, 1956-1964 (Box 43-44.)
    - A Survey of Recent Developments in Nine Captive Nations, 1956-1964 (Contd.) (Box 45., Folder 1)
  - Reports related to Eastern Europe (Folder 2)
  - Resolutions and reports, 1955-1963 (Folder 3)
  - Special session transcripts, 1954-1963 (Box 46-47.)
  - Statements, including by Coste (Box 48., Folder 1-2)
  - Writings of Coste about the A.C.E.N.
    - Addresses (Folder 3)
    - Notes (Folder 4)